Derek Mahon papers, circa 1948-2008
Emory University
- Writings by Derek Mahon, 1976-2007, Series 2; Box 17 - Box 35 (folder 6); OP1-3
  - Poems, Subseries 2.1; Box 17 - Box 23 (folder 6); OP1-2
    - Collected poems, Subseries 2.1a; Box 17 - Box 22 (folder 33); OP1-2
      - The Seaside Cemetery, TS (Box 20, Folder 36)
      - The Seaside Cemetery, uncorrected proof (Box 20, Folder 37)
      - The Seaside Cemetery, corrected proof (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - The Seaside Cemetery, research material: "Concerning Le Cimetière Marin" in Valéry's The Art of Poetry," photocopy (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Birds by Saint-John Perse: A Version by Derek Mahon (2002)
      - Saint-John Perse's Oiseaux (1963) (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Birds, Robert Fitzgerald's translation, photocopy (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Birds, Robert Fitgerald TS with Mahon MS (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Birds, TS [1] (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Birds, TS [2] (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Birds, TS [3] (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Birds, TS [4] (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Birds, TS [5] (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Birds, Translator's Note, TS (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Birds, proof (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Birds, jacket copy (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Birds, research materials (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Harbour Lights (2005)
      - "Bash? in Kinsale," TS (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - "Calypso," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - "The Cloud Ceiling," TS (Box 21, Folder 17)
      - "During the War," MS, TS, and proof (Box 21, Folder 18)
      - "The Enchanted Wood," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 19)
      - "A Game of Cards," TS [includes ALS, 30 April 2001, and research materials] (Box 21, Folder 20)
      - "A Garden God," TS (Box 21, Folder 21)
      - "Hampstead Graves," TS (Box 21, Folder 22)
      - "Harbour Lights," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 23)
      - "Heathrow," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 24)
      - "High Water," TS (Box 21, Folder 25)
      - "Jean Rhys in Kettner's," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 26)
      - "Langue d'Oc," MS and TS [variant title: "Spring Song" in Adaptations] (Box 21, Folder 27)
      - "Lapis Lazuli," TS (Box 21, Folder 28)
      - "Lucretius on Clouds," TS and proofs [includes ALS from Maeve and research materials] (Box 21, Folder 29)
      - "New Wave," MS, TS, and proof (Box 21, Folder 30)
      - "On the Beach" [See "Shorelines"] (Box -, -)
      - "Red Cloud," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 31)
      - "Shorelines," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 32)
      - "'Things,'" TS (Box 21, Folder 33)
      - "Where to Hide," TS (Box 21, Folder 34)
      - "White Cloud," TS (Box 21, Folder 35)
      - "The Widow of Kinsale," MS and TS (Box 21, Folder 36)
      - Harbour Lights, TS with corrections [1] (Box 21a, Folder 1)
      - Harbour Lights, TS with corrections [2] (Box 21a, Folder 2)
      - Harbour Lights, TS with corrections [3] (Box 21a, Folder 3)
      - Harbour Lights, TS and proof (Box 21a, Folder 4)
      - Harbour Lights, proof with corrections (Box 21a, Folder 5)
      - Harbour Lights, proof (Box 21a, Folder 6)
      - Harbour Lights, covers [with ALS from Peter Fallon, 7 February 2005] (Box 21a, Folder 7)
      - Harbour Lights, epigraph, MS and TS (Box 21a, Folder 8)
      - Harbour Lights, notes and research material (Box 21a, Folder 9)
      - Selected Poems, Expanded Edition (2006)
      - Selected Poems (2006), proof with corrections [1 of 2] [with TLS from Sarah Hulbert, 17 November 2005] (Box 21a, Folder 10)
      - Selected Poems (2006), proof with corrections [2 of 2] (Box 21a, Folder 11)
      - Selected Poems (2006), covers [with ALS (undated) and TLS (12 July 2005) from Zelda Turner] (Box 21a, Folder 12)
      - Adaptations (2006)
      - "Ariel to Prospero," MS and TS and proof [see also "A Rilke Sequence"] (Box 21a, Folder 13)
      - "The Bangor Blackbird," TS [see also "From The Bangor Antiphonary"] (Box 21a, Folder 14)
      - "Borgeby-Gard," MS and TS [see also "A Rilke Sequence"] (Box 21a, Folder 15)
      - "Chorus from Antigone," MS and TS and proof (Box 21a, Folder 16)
      - "Chorus from Oedipus at Colonus," TS (Box 21a, Folder 17)
      - "The Cloud," TS (Box 21a, Folder 18)
      - "Dawn Songs," TS (Box 21a, Folder 19)
      - "From The Bangor Antiphonary," TS [includes 2 TLS, 24 January 2006 and 26 March 2006, from Kenneth Irvine and research materials] (Box 21a, Folder 20)
      - "Jardin du Luxembourg," MS and TS [see also "A Rilke Sequence"] (Box 21a, Folder 21)
      - "Love in the Afternoon," MS and TS (Box 21a, Folder 22)
      - "Night Drive," TS [see also "A Rilke Sequence"] (Box 21a, Folder 23)
      - "Night Watch," MS and TS [see also "A Rilke Sequence"] (Box 21a, Folder 24)
      - "Red Cloud," proof (Box 21a, Folder 25)
      - "A Rilke Sequence," TS [see also "Ariel to Prospero," "Borgeby-Gard," "Jardin du Luxembourg," "Night Drive, and "Night Watch"] (Box 21a, Folder 26)
      - "Two from Burbles," MS and TS (Box 21a, Folder 27)
      - "Women in Love," MS and TS (Box 21a, Folder 28)
      - "Women in Love" (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - "The Young Cordwainer," TS (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Adaptations, proof (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Adaptations, Acknowledgments, TS (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Adaptations, Foreword, TS (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Adaptations, jacket copy [includes 2 ALS, 7 April 2006 and 22 March 2006, from Peter Fallon] (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Adaptations, Table of Contents, MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Art Notes (2006)
      - "Birds," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - "Cushendun in Winter," TS (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - "A Lighthouse in Maine," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - "Rain," TS (Box 22, Folder 11)
      - "The Realm of Light," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - "Savannah Dock," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - "Studio in Antibes," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1a, Art Notes, "Triptych"] (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - "Triptych," TS (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - "Wave Shadow," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Art Notes, TS with corrections [1] (Box 22, Folder 17)
      - Art Notes, TS with corrections [2] (Box 22, Folder 18)
      - Art Notes, proofs [with ALS from Peter Fallon, 3 October 2006] (Box 22, Folder 19)
      - Art Notes, proofs of drawings by Vivienne Roche [with ALS from Peter Fallon, 9 October 2006] (Box 22, Folder 20)
      - Art Notes, table of contents (Box 22, Folder 21)
      - Somewhere the Wave (2007)
      - "Biographia Literaria," TS (Box 22, Folder 22)
      - "Brian Moore's Belfast," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 23)
      - "Circe's Cup," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 24)
      - "Goa," TS [See also Subseries 2.1a, Somewhere the Wave, "Tara Boulevard"] (Box 22, Folder 25)
      - "The Lady from the Sea," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1b, "The Dying Mermaid"] (Box 22, Folder 26)
      - "Quaderno," MS and TS [variant title: "From 'The Italian Job'"] [includes "An Ice-Cream at Caproni's," "Beyond the Alps," "Casa Sul Mare," "Diogenes on the Shore," "Geronimo," "Pasolini," "I Pensierosi," "Paolo and Lighea," "Beatrice Hastings," and "…Dove Per Sole…"] (Box 22, Folder 27)
      - "The Seagull," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 28)
      - "Somewhere the Wave," MS, TS, and proof [with ALS from Richard Keith, undated] (Box 22, Folder 29)
      - "Tara Boulevard," TS [variant title: "Gone with the Wind"] [See also Subseries 2.1a, Somewhere the Wave, "Somewhere the Wave"] (Box 22, Folder 30)
      - Somewhere the Wave, TS with corrections (Box 22, Folder 31)
      - Somewhere the Wave, proofs of drawings and watercolors by Bernadette Kiely (Box 22, Folder 32)
      - Somewhere the Wave, table of contents (Box 22, Folder 33)
    - Uncollected poems, Subseries 2.1b; Box 22 (folder 34) - Box 23 (folder 6)
      - "After Cavafy," MS (Box 22, Folder 34)
      - "Amour de Loin," TS [partial translation of Jaufré Rudel] (Box 22, Folder 35)
      - "Anabasis," TS (Box 22, Folder 36)
      - "Anti-Tractatus," MS (Box 22, Folder 37)
      - "Autumn Day," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 38)
      - "Barbara" (after Prévert), MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 39)
      - "Beyond the Pale," proof (Box 22, Folder 40)
      - "Breath Tanka," TS (Box 22, Folder 41)
      - "Choruses from 'The Bacchae,'" MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 42)
      - "A Christmas Carol," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 43)
      - "The Clifden Road," TS (Box 22, Folder 44)
      - "The Coastguard House," TS (Box 22, Folder 45)
      - "Day and Night," TS (Box 22, Folder 46)
      - "Decadent Ball," TS [translation of D'Adoré Floupette] (Box 22, Folder 47)
      - "Dirigibles," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 48)
      - "Dove(s); A Dove (Homage to Elizabeth Bishop)," TS (Box 22, Folder 49)
      - "Driving in Ulster," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 50)
      - "Drying Out," MS and TS (Box 22, Folder 51)
      - "The Dying Mermaid," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1a, Somewhere the Wave, "The Lady from the Sea"] (Box 22, Folder 52)
      - "Elevation," photocopy with corrections (Box 22, Folder 53)
      - "Fall-Out," MS (Box 22, Folder 54)
      - "From Winds" (after Saint-John Perse), TS (Box 22, Folder 55)
      - "Goethe's Orphic Words," TS [variant title: "Goethe on Orphic Wisdom"] (Box 22a, Folder 1)
      - "Grand Central," TS (Box 22a, Folder 2)
      - "Hiroshima," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 3)
      - "L'Hiver qui Vient," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 4)
      - "Homage to Paul Éluard," TS (Box 22a, Folder 5)
      - "Hotel Columbus," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 6)
      - "The Houses of Corr an Chait," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 7)
      - "Jack Holland," TS (Box 22a, Folder 8)
      - "Kafka's Sirens," TS [includes photocopy of Franz Kafka's "The Silence of the Sirens" with annotations by Mahon] (Box 22a, Folder 9)
      - "La Dolce Vita," TS (Box 22a, Folder 10)
      - "The Last Bard" [See "Swift's Dublin"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "London Rain," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 11)
      - "The Long Goodbye," MS (Box 22a, Folder 12)
      - "Louis and Sam," TS (Box 22a, Folder 13)
      - "Mary Barbour," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 14)
      - "A Midsummer Night's Dream," MS (Box 22a, Folder 15)
      - "A Morning Star," TS (Box 22a, Folder 16)
      - "The Mountains of Egypt," TS (Box 22a, Folder 17)
      - "Nacht und Träume," MS and TS [variant title: "Scream Dream"] (Box 22a, Folder 18)
      - "A New Watch," TS (Box 22a, Folder 19)
      - "New York Laundry," TS (Box 22a, Folder 20)
      - "Nightwood," TS (Box 22a, Folder 21)
      - "Night and Day," TS (Box 22a, Folder 22)
      - "Niobe," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 23)
      - "No Incinerator," TS (Box 22a, Folder 24)
      - "Ode to Björk," TS (Box 22a, Folder 25)
      - "On Belgian Cuisine," [Baudelaire translation], TS (Box 22a, Folder 26)
      - "Patrick Kavanagh," TS (Box 22a, Folder 27)
      - "Petrarch's Lament," TS (Box 22a, Folder 28)
      - "The Petrified Forest," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 29)
      - "The Pine-Wood Notebook," [Ponge translation], MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 30)
      - "A Place," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 31)
      - "XLIX Poison," MS and TS [translation of Baudelaire] (Box 22a, Folder 32)
      - "Portrait of a Woman (Pompeii)," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 33)
      - "Radio Times," TS (Box 22a, Folder 34)
      - "Recognition," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 35)
      - "Sand and Stars," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 36)
      - "Sandy Cove," MS notes (Box 22a, Folder 37)
      - "Sappho's Lyre," MS (Box 22a, Folder 38)
      - "Sea-Coast of Bohemia," TS (Box 22a, Folder 39)
      - "The Sea House," TS (Box 22a, Folder 40)
      - "A Silent House," TS [variant title: "Rincurran Cottage"] (Box 22a, Folder 41)
      - "Six Clerihews for Oscar Wilde," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 42)
      - "Some Sunny Day," TS (Box 22a, Folder 43)
      - "Squares," MS (Box 22a, Folder 44)
      - "The Statues," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 45)
      - "Sun Song," TS (Box 22a, Folder 46)
      - "Survivor," MS (Box 22a, Folder 47)
      - "Swift's Dublin" and "The Last Bard," TS (Box 22a, Folder 48)
      - "Times have changed," TS (Box 22a, Folder 49)
      - "To an 'Old Friend,'" TS (Box 22a, Folder 50)
      - "To Aunt Louise," TS and photograph (Box 22a, Folder 51)
      - "To the Voice of Kathleen Ferrier," TS (Box 22a, Folder 52)
      - "Towards the Light," TS (Box 22a, Folder 53)
      - "Two Poems by Dino Campana," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 54)
      - "Two Poems by Mathieu Bénézet," TS (Box 22a, Folder 55)
      - "Two Traditions," TS (Box 22a, Folder 56)
      - "Ursula's Place," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 57)
      - "Washington Sq.," TS (Box 22a, Folder 58)
      - "Wind and Wave," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 59)
      - "Window in Fiesole," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 60)
      - "Winter Sunset" (after Laforgue), TS (Box 22a, Folder 61)
      - Untitled
      - "Dawn, and the brightest sun," TS (Box 22a, Folder 62)
      - "A first garden then", TS (Box 22a, Folder 63)
      - "Grave and resourceful, visibly reserved," TS (Box 22a, Folder 64)
      - "I showed up in an era," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 65)
      - "I walk alone in the spring wood," TS (Box 22a, Folder 66)
      - "I watch you sleeping while the sun rises," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 67)
      - "Immured in her dark tower," TS (Box 22a, Folder 68)
      - "In my seashaken house," TS (Box 22a, Folder 69)
      - "On the final capes of exile I raise my hand for the last time," TS (Box 22a, Folder 70)
      - "Presently industrial suburbs", MS (Box 22a, Folder 71)
      - "Pygmalion, having watched the Propoetides," MS (Box 22a, Folder 72)
      - "They live the hours as others live the years," TS (Box 22a, Folder 73)
      - "Turf fires still glowing in our cindery grates," TS (Box 22a, Folder 74)
      - "Walpurgisnacht at noon under the low ceiling," MS and TS (Box 22a, Folder 75)
      - Three translations by DM of poems by Denis Rizal, TS (Box 22a, Folder 76)
      - Fragments and notes (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Notes (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Notes (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Notes, 2000-2006 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Notebooks (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Notebook, circa 2000 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Prose, Subseries 2.2; Box 23 (folder 7) - Box 26 (folder 6)
    - Acceptance speech for David Cohen Prize, 2007, MS and TS (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Alternative Voices [review of Flotsam and Jetsam, Donkey's Years, and Dog Days, by Aidan Higgins] and associated material (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Auden on St. Mark's Place (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - "Autumn Blues" [translation of Mallarmé's "Plainte d'Automne"], TS (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - "Betjeman in Dublin," MS and TS (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Christmas Books, December 1993 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - "Christmas Books," TS (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Closing Down Kinsale (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Coca-Cola, [review of Under the Volcano, dir. by John Huston (based on the novel by Malcolm Lowry)], corrected typescript with promotional material (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - The Double Dactyl (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Dublin's Shelbourne Hotel (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - An Empire of Signs [article re: Edinburgh Festival], corrected typescript with proof (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Epiphanies [review of Tilting the Jar, Spilling the Moon] (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Euphorion in Ely Place [essay on George Moore] and preparatory notes (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - A Fitting Tribute [review of Decantations, ed. by Agnes Bernelle] (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Foreword to projected collection of Selected Prose (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Foreword to J. G. Farrell: The Making of a Writer, by Lavinia Greacen, and associated material (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - Foreword to An Unweaving of Rainbows, by John Minihan, and associated material (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Foreword to Wildly for Days, by Eamon Grennan, corrected typescript (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - "A Ghostly Rumble Among the Drums" [article about Mahon's experiences at Trinity College, Dublin], TS (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - "A Goofy Delinquent" [review of Slow Learner: Early Stories by Thomas Pynchon], TS (Box 23, Folder 27)
    - "Gravity and Grace: The Art of Anne Madden," MS and TS (Box 23, Folder 28)
    - The Heat of the Day [review of The Heat of the Day, by Elizabeth Bowen], corrected typescript (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - "The Heaven of Painting" [translation of Marcelin Pleynet's "Le Ciel de la Peinture" about Anne Madden], MS and TS (Box 23, Folder 30)
    - High Time [program note], corrected typescript (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - "The Girl on the Bridge," TS (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - His Own Worst Enemy [review of Alexander the Great, by John Maxwell O'Brien] (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Icarus (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - An Imprudential Poet [review of Poems, by W.R. Rodgers] (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - [Introduction for Aidan Higgins] (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - [Introduction for Aidan Mathews] (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - [Introduction for Ciaran Carson and Nuala Ni Dhomnhaill] (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - [Introduction for Daniel Albright] (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - [Introduction for Edna O'Brien] (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - [Introduction for Seamus Deane] (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - The King and I [1996 Yeats International Summer School lecture] (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Letter from New York: The Mag Trade, January 1993 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Letter from New York: [Race Matters], 25 January 1993 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Letter from New York: Lit City, 26 April 1993 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Letter from New York: Bright Lights, June 1993 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Letter from New York: Thanks for Sharing, June 1993 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - Letter from New York: Unseen Worlds, 26 October 1993 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Letter from New York: John Butler Yeats in NYC, 27 November 1993 (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Letter from New York: Just Kidding, 21 February 1994 (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - Letter from New York: Lotus Land, 27 March 1994 (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - Letter from New York: Scorpio Rising, 23 April 1994 (Box 24, Folder 22)
    - Letter from New York: [Samuel Beckett], 26 April 1994 (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - Letter from New York: Thanks for Sharing; Prizes for all, 24 May 1994 (Box 24, Folder 24)
    - Letter from New York: Patriotic Gore, 6 June 1994 (Box 24, Folder 25)
    - Letter from New York: Girl Crazy, Cracking Wise, Ogdenational, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 26)
    - Letter from New York: Passion and Irony, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 27)
    - Letter from New York: Unseen Worlds, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 28)
    - Letter from New York: Upstarts from Ireland, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 29)
    - Louis MacNeice and Gypsy Rose Lee (Box 24, Folder 30)
    - A Month at Yaddo (Box 24, Folder 31)
    - The Mother of Invention: Freedom and Necessity in Contemporary Irish Poetry (Box 24, Folder 32)
    - The Mother of Invention: Freedom and Necessity in Contemporary Irish Poetry [revised version] (Box 24, Folder 33)
    - Muldoon (Box 24, Folder 34)
    - New York Irish Chic (Box 24, Folder 35)
    - No Access to the Tomb in High Brazil (Box 24, Folder 36)
    - A Noise Like Wings [article re: Samuel Beckett], corrected typescripts with related correspondence and photocopy of published article (Box 24, Folder 37)
    - Paris Diary, corrected typescripts with proof (Box 24, Folder 38)
    - Prague Spring (Box 24, Folder 39)
    - Preface to Gérard de Nerval, Les Chimères, TS (Box 24, Folder 40)
    - Preface to The Strings Are False by Louis MacNeice, 2007, MS and TS (Box 24, Folder 41)
    - "The Pre-Natal Mountain: Louis MacNeice's Ireland," TS (Box 24, Folder 42)
    - Quaat? [review of Quoof, by Paul Muldoon], corrected typescripts with clipping (Box 24, Folder 43)
    - "A Record of Writerly Thought" [review of Windy Arbours: Collected Criticism by Aidan Higgins], TS [includes ALS, 15 February 2006, from Higgins] (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Rome and Music (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Sam – the artist as hero [review of Samuel Beckett: The Last Modernist by Anthony Cronin] (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Samuel Menashe (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - A Secular Mystic [on Philippe Jaccottet] (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - "Spice of Life" [review of Collected Poems by Louis MacNeice], 2007, TS (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - The Titanic (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - To Get the Moment Back [review of Desire in Belfast, by Sean Haldane] (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Traces Elements of the Race [review of A Snail in My Prime, by Paul Durcan] (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - "War and Peace" [review of Collected Poems by Michael Longley], TS (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - "Waste Is the Better Part of Wisdom" [essay about Patrick MacDonogh for the PBS Bulletin, Winter 2000], TS and proof (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - "Watt Is the Word" [article about Samuel Beckett's poetry], 2006, MS and TS (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Womanly Times [review of Between Moon and Moon: Selected Letters of Robert Graves], corrected typescript (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Verse Drama [Exiles Theatre Festival 1995] (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - "Yeats, Belfast and Dublin in the Sixties" [lecture delivered at the Yeats Summer School, Sligo, August 1996], TS [later published as "Yeats and the Lights of Dublin" in The Dublin Review, Autumn 2002] (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - "Yeats and the Lights of Dublin," TS [includes TLS, 11 July 2002, from Brendan Barrington about the essay's publication in The Dublin Review] (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Young Eavan and Early Boland (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - Untitled [re: Glyn Hughes and Tony Harrison], circa 1970 (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Untitled [re: John Banville] (Box 25, Folder 19)
    - Untitled [re: Poems, 1962-1978] (Box 25, Folder 20)
    - Untitled [reflection on Night-Crossing], 1968, TS (Box 25, Folder 21)
    - Untitled [review of Camus, by Patrick McCarthy, and An Ice Cream War, by William Boyd], corrected typescript (Box 25, Folder 22)
    - Untitled [review of Collected Poems, by Anthony Cronin], TS (Box 25, Folder 23)
    - Untitled [review of Langrishe, Go Down, by Aidan Higgins] (Box 25, Folder 24)
    - Untitled [article on Aran Islands] (Box 25, Folder 25)
    - Untitled [sleeve notes for Jack MacGowran speaking Samuel Beckett's poetry], TS [includes correspondence from Richard Ryan and Mahon] (Box 25, Folder 26)
    - Untitled [Sunday Independent Books of the Year] (Box 25, Folder 27)
    - Untitled [series of pensées] (Box 25, Folder 28)
    - Untitled [fragment of essay on MacNeice and Auden] (Box 25, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified fragments (Box 25, Folder 30)
    - Notes towards Memoir 1941-1980 (Box 25, Folder 31)
    - Notes on Mangan (Box 25, Folder 32)
    - Notes on Milan Kundera's Unbearable Lightness of Being (Box 25, Folder 33)
    - Notes on "Snow" by Louis MacNeice (Box 25, Folder 34)
    - Scrapbook, 1996-1997 [includes Yellow Book materials] (Box 25, Folder 35)
    - Dublin Diary September 1997-June 1999 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Preface to Journalism (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Journalism notes by Terence Brown and Derek Mahon (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Journalism notes (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Journalism proofs (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Journalism proposed dustjackets (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Scripts and screenplays, Subseries 2.3; Box 26 (folder 7) - Box 31; OP3
    - The Bacchae, typescript with corrections (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - The Bacchae, typescript with corrections (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - The Bacchae, typescript fragment (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - The Bacchae, "Rachael's thoughts" (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - The Bacchae [script for RTE transmission, October 2000] (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Come Back Early or Never Come [re: Louis MacNeice], film proposal (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - The Cry [adaptation of short story by John Montague], corrected typescript (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - The Cry, "2nd draft," photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - The Cry, "rehearsal script" with corrections (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Cyrano de Bergerac, MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Cyrano de Bergerac, MS and TS (Box 26, Folder 17)